<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000169</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-72</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000169</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Collaborative Longitudinal Evaluation of Ethnicity and Refractive Error (CLEERE) Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare and contrast normal eye growth, ocular component development, and refractive error
      development in Hispanic, African-American, and Asian schoolchildren with what happens in
      Caucasian children from the Orinda Longitudinal Study of Myopia.

      To investigate risk factors for the development of myopia.

      To conduct DNA-based studies on nearsighted children and their families.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Orinda Longitudinal Study of Myopia (OLSM) was started in 1989 to investigate normal eye
      growth and the development of myopia in over 1,200 school-aged children to date. Beginning in
      1997, three parallel study phases are being conducted. Phase 1 investigates additional
      factors that may predict the onset of juvenile myopia (accommodative function, peripheral
      refractive error, intraocular pressure, and school achievement). Phase 2 compares and
      contrasts the optical ocular components and refractive error profiles of other ethnic groups
      with the predominantly Caucasian Orinda database. Phase 3 conducts DNA-based studies on the
      prevalent OLSM myopes and their families to use these phenotypically well-characterized
      children and a panel of candidate genes to look for evidence of genetic factors. In parallel
      with the candidate gene association, family material is used in an allele sharing approach to
      identify loci using highly variable, PCR-based markers.

      In Phase 1 we continue to examine Orinda Union School District children in grades 1 through 8
      (ages 6 through 14 years) annually. The measurement of accommodative response, accommodative
      lag, phoria, response AC/A ratio, peripheral refractive error, and intraocular pressure will
      be added to the existing protocol, and photokeratoscopy and two measures of tonic
      accommodation will be eliminated to minimize respondent burden. Parents of children in the
      study will be contacted for their permission to release school achievement data (Iowa Test of
      Basic Skills).

      Phase 2 adds a major component by adding three clinical centers to assess the influence of
      ethnicity on normal ocular and refractive error development. Children in these three are
      examined annually with initial enrollment in all grades from 1 through 8 using the revised
      OLSM protocol as described above.

      Increased prevalence of myopia among children of myopic parents, twin studies, segregation
      analysis, and our own preliminary analyses from the OLSM support a genetic etiologic
      component for myopia. In phase 3, we use the phenotypic characterization of children in the
      Orinda Longitudinal Study of Myopia to identify prevalent cases of myopia and their families.
      These well-defined phenotypic myopes and non-myopic siblings and their parents are being
      explored, seeking to develop a panel of candidate genes for myopia and to conduct an allele
      sharing analysis in these families

      The Collaborative Longitudinal Evaluation of Ethnicity and Refractive Error (CLEERE) Study is
      a multi-center, observational investigation of ocular development and refractive error
      development in schoolchildren. It adds three clinical centers to the Orinda Longitudinal
      Study of Myopia (OLSM), begun in 1989, specifically to describe normal ocular growth in
      children ages 6 to 14 years, and to develop the ability to predict juvenile onset myopia
      before it is clinically evident. In addition to the more than 1,300 predominantly Caucasian
      children enrolled in the OLSM, three additional clinical sites enroll African-American,
      Hispanic, and Asian children. The children are examined annually for at least four years.
      Examinations include visual acuity, refraction by a variety of methods (cycloplegic
      autorefraction being the primary outcome measure), cover test at distance and near,
      accommodative response assessment with the autorefractor, response AC/A ratio measurement,
      videophakometry, peripheral refraction, and A-scan ultrasonography.

      Patients are examined at 4 clinical centers. The clinical centers have enrolled 3,493
      patients as of April 28, 1999.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 1999</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Children were eligible if they were enrolled in the first through eighth grades in selected
        schools in Eutaw, Alabama; Houston, Texas; Orinda, California; or Irvine, California in the
        1997-98 academic year and in the first grade only in Eutaw, Houston, and Irvine in the
        1998-99 academic year.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa A. Jones, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>1-614-292-7097</phone>
    <email>jones.809@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Alabama Health Services, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eutaw</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35462</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandral Hullett, MD, et al</last_name>
      <phone>205-372-3674</phone>
      <email>kleinstein@icare.opt.uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southern California College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fullerton</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92831</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie A. Yu, OD</last_name>
      <phone>714-992-7806</phone>
      <email>jyu@scco.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Houston, College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77204-2020</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ruth E. Manny, OD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>713-743-1944</phone>
      <email>rmanny@uh.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutti DO, Zadnik K, Adams AJ. A video technique for phakometry of the human crystalline lens. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1992 Apr;33(5):1771-82.</citation>
    <PMID>1559777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Mutti DO, Adams AJ. The repeatability of measurement of the ocular components. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1992 Jun;33(7):2325-33.</citation>
    <PMID>1607244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walline JJ, Zadnik K, Mutti DO. Validity of surveys reporting myopia, astigmatism, and presbyopia. Optom Vis Sci. 1996 Jun;73(6):376-81.</citation>
    <PMID>8807648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Mutti DO, Friedman NE, Adams AJ. Initial cross-sectional results from the Orinda Longitudinal Study of Myopia. Optom Vis Sci. 1993 Sep;70(9):750-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8233371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Satariano WA, Mutti DO, Sholtz RI, Adams AJ. The effect of parental history of myopia on children's eye size. JAMA. 1994 May 4;271(17):1323-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8158816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Friedman NE, Mutti DO. Repeatability of corneal topography: the &quot;corneal field&quot;. J Refract Surg. 1995 Mar-Apr;11(2):119-25. Erratum in: J Refract Surg 1995 May-Jun;11(3):164.</citation>
    <PMID>7634141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutti DO, Zadnik K, Adams AJ. The equivalent refractive index of the crystalline lens in childhood. Vision Res. 1995 Jun;35(11):1565-73.</citation>
    <PMID>7667914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Mutti DO, Fusaro RE, Adams AJ. Longitudinal evidence of crystalline lens thinning in children. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1995 Jul;36(8):1581-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7601639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedman NE, Zadnik K, Mutti DO, Fusaro RE. Quantifying corneal toricity from videokeratography with Fourier analysis. J Refract Surg. 1996 Jan-Feb;12(1):108-13.</citation>
    <PMID>8963798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedman NE, Mutti DO, Zadnik K. Corneal changes in schoolchildren. Optom Vis Sci. 1996 Aug;73(8):552-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8869987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutti DO, Zadnik K, Fusaro RE, Friedman NE, Sholtz RI, Adams AJ. Optical and structural development of the crystalline lens in childhood. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1998 Jan;39(1):120-33.</citation>
    <PMID>9430553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kleinstein RN, Mutti DO, Manny RE, Shin JA, Zadnik K. Cycloplegia in African-American children. Optom Vis Sci. 1999 Feb;76(2):102-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10082056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shin JA, Manny RE, Kleinstein RN, Mutti DO, Zadnik K. Short-term repeatability of hand-held keratometry measurements. Optom Vis Sci. 1999 Apr;76(4):247-53.</citation>
    <PMID>10333188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Mutti DO, Kim HS, Jones LA, Qiu PH, Moeschberger ML. Tonic accommodation, age, and refractive error in children. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1999 May;40(6):1050-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10235538</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Mutti DO, Friedman NE, Qualley PA, Jones LA, Qui P, Kim HS, Hsu JC, Moeschberger ML. Ocular predictors of the onset of juvenile myopia. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1999 Aug;40(9):1936-43.</citation>
    <PMID>10440246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2001</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

