<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000117</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000117</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravenous Immunoglobulin Therapy in Optic Neuritis</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether high-dose intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIg) is more effective than
      placebo in restoring lost visual function (visual acuity) in optic neuritis (ON).

      To determine the time course of recovery following IVIg administration. If the reports of
      IVIg-associated clinical improvement occurring within 3 to 6 months following treatment can
      be confirmed, this would provide indirect evidence that IVIg may promote central nervous
      system (CNS) remyelination in optic neuritis and multiple sclerosis (MS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Optic neuritis is the leading cause of transient, spontaneous, reversible visual loss in
      young adults. Characteristically, patients present with central visual loss that peaks within
      a few days and is often associated with eye pain. Visual loss may be complete. Spontaneous
      recovery usually begins within 4 weeks, and marked recovery occurs within 1 to 3 months in
      most patients. Although clinical improvement is the rule, not all patients recover fully, and
      many are left with residual symptoms. Although there are limited pathological studies in
      inflammatory ON, the pathological changes are thought to be virtually identical with those
      seen in MS, with disruption of the blood-nerve (brain) barrier; primary demyelination with
      axonal sparing; variable degrees of lymphocytic infiltration; an abundance of macrophages
      around the inflammatory demyelination lesion; various degrees of remyelination; and, later,
      oligodendrocyte loss, axonal loss, and gliosis.

      Remyelination by oligodendrocytes occurs early in the MS lesion, as documented by myelin
      sheaths that are abnormally thin relative to axon diameter. These thin myelin sheaths are
      often seen prominently at the edge of demyelinated plaques. A recent series of studies has
      shown that within weeks of the initial event, there is extensive oligodendrocyte regeneration
      and remyelination. These immature oligodendrocytes express a series of developmentally
      restricted antigens. This finding has been interpreted to suggest that the cells that
      repopulate the acute plaque and that affect remyelination are newly generated and not
      residual, mature oligodendrocytes. These observations support the possibility that factors
      that promote remyelination could be used to improve clinical recovery in ON and MS.

      Work at the Mayo Clinic, has shown that both immunoglobulin G (IgG) directed against spinal
      cord antigens and purified polyclonal mouse IgG administered systemically promote extensive
      remyelination in SJL mice chronically infected with Theiler's virus. In addition, tissue
      culture studies suggest that IgG directed against CNS components may promote oligodendroglial
      proliferation and differentiation. Thus, experimental evidence exists for the concept that
      immunoglobulins may stimulate the proliferation and differentiation of oligodendrocytes. It
      is possible that myelin components on the surface of oligodendrocytes could function as
      receptors or components of receptors. Antibodies could mimic endogenous ligands, thereby
      inducing the proliferation or differentiation of these cells.

      In a preliminary, open-label pilot study of patients with chronic, steroid-unresponsive ON,
      Drs. van Engelen, Hommes, and colleagues suggested that improvement in visual recovery could
      be seen following IgG treatment in patients with chronic, stable ON. These encouraging but
      preliminary basic and clinical studies have prompted us to design a double-blind and
      placebo-controlled clinical trial of IVIg in patients with recently acquired but apparently
      permanent muscle paralysis from MS (NS31506) and to develop this NEI-funded ON study
      (U10EY1096301).

      In this randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trial, 60 patients were
      assigned to receive either IVIg or a placebo over a period of 3 months. In order to be
      eligible, patients who meet the inclusion criteria needed to have a stable loss of visual
      function (unchanged between the pre-enrollment screening visit and the enrollment visit). All
      patients wre re-examined at 3, 6, 9, and 12 months, with the primary outcome being the impact
      of treatment on visual acuity at 6 months as determined by measurements on a retroilluminated
      Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study chart at 4 meters.

      One group of patients received 0.4 g/kg Gammimmune N intravenously daily for 5 days, and
      thereafter once a month for 3 months (total: eight infusions). The other group of patients
      received infusions of 0.1 percent human serum albumin in 10 percent maltose (placebo)
      according to the identical protocol used for Gammimmune N.

      The primary outcome measure was improvement in Logmar visual acuity by an average of 0.2 at 6
      months. The secondary outcome measures included change in visual acuity at 3, 9, and 12
      months, as determined on a retroilluminated ETDRS chart at 4 meters; change in visual fields
      at 6 and 12 months; change in visual evoked responses at 3, 6, and 12 months; and change in
      neurological examination (EDSS, FS, AI) at 3, 6, 9, and 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 1997</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Optic Neuritis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immunoglobulin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        To be eligible, patients must have a history of one or more episodes of previous
        demyelinating optic neuritis occurring in the setting of classic, adult-onset definite MS
        (clinically definite or laboratory-supported definite MS, or cranial MRI changes consistent
        with MS). In most cases, onset of MS will have occurred between the ages of 18 and 45.
        Patients must be younger than 50 years and must have apparently irreversible loss of visual
        acuity that meets the following criteria:

        Visual acuity must be worse than 20/40 for at least 6 months. Patients must be able to read
        at least one letter on the 1-meter eye chart. Patients with no light perception or hand
        movement vision only are not eligible.

        The above level of visual dysfunction must be observed on at least two serial examinations
        (separated by at least 1 month) in the Department of Ophthalmology at the Mayo Clinic.

        Optic disc pallor must be present.

        Patients must have impairment in the affected eye(s) on perimetry consistent with optic
        nerve dysfunction and must have a visual field mean deviation of less than -4.00.

        Patients must not have received ACTH or corticosteroids within the preceding 2 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic, Department of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>gamma-Globulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rho(D) Immune Globulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

