<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000114</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000114</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Trial of Vitamin A and Vitamin E Supplementation for Retinitis Pigmentosa</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether supplements of vitamin A or vitamin E alone or in combination affect the
      course of retinitis pigmentosa.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Retinitis pigmentosa (RP) is a group of inherited retinal degenerations with a worldwide
      prevalence of about 1 in 4,000. Patients typically report night blindness in adolescence and
      lose vision in the midperipheral followed by far-peripheral visual field in adulthood due to
      progressive loss of both rod and cone function. Most patients have reductions in central
      vision by age 50 to 80 years. Modern-day electroretinograms (ERGs) make it possible to record
      retinal responses from most patients with remaining vision and thereby monitor objectively
      the course of their disease.

      While the natural course of retinal degeneration in the common forms of RP was being studied,
      it was noted that a subgroup of patients aged 18 through 49 who were treating themselves with
      both vitamin A and vitamin E and other nutritional supplements exhibited less decline in ERG
      amplitude over a 2-year period. These preliminary findings, as well as the known roles of
      vitamins A and E in maintaining normal photoreceptor function and structure, prompted this
      randomized, controlled trial to determine whether these vitamins alone or in combination
      would halt or slow the progression of the common forms of RP.

      This study was a randomized, controlled double-masked trial with 2 x 2 factorial design and
      duration of 4 to 6 years. Patients were assigned to one of four treatment groups:

      15,000 IU/day vitamin A

      15,000 IU/day vitamin A + 400 IU/day vitamin E

      trace amounts of both vitamins A and E

      400 IU/day of vitamin E

      The main outcome measure was the 30-Hz cone ERG amplitude. In addition, visual field and
      visual acuity were measured annually.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1984</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1987</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Retinitis Pigmentosa</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin E</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin A</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and nonpregnant women between ages 18 and 49 years with common forms of RP were
        included. All eligible patients had retinal arteriolar attenuation, elevated dark
        adaptation thresholds, and reduced ERGs. Patients had best corrected Snellen visual acuity
        of 20/100 or better, central visual field diameter on the Goldman perimeter with V4 e white
        test light of 8 degrees or greater, and ERG amplitude of 2.5 or greater in response to
        0.5-Hz white light or of 0.12 ultraviolet light or greater in response to 30-Hz white
        flickering light in at least one eye. In addition, patients had normal fasting serum
        retinol and serum liver function profile and weight above the lower fifth percentile for
        age, sex, and height. All patients had a total estimated pre-trial intake of vitamins A and
        E from diet plus pills not greater than 11,500 IU/day and 40 IU/day, respectively.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/clinicalalerts/alert-rp.asp</url>
    <description>Clinical Alert-Information for Doctors Who Follow Patients with Retinitis Pigmentosa</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/rppressrelease.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Treatment for Retinitis Pigmentosa Reported</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berson EL, Rosner B, Sandberg MA, Hayes KC, Nicholson BW, Weigel-DiFranco C, Willett W. A randomized trial of vitamin A and vitamin E supplementation for retinitis pigmentosa. Arch Ophthalmol. 1993 Jun;111(6):761-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8512476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandberg MA, Weigel-DiFranco C, Rosner B, Berson EL. The relationship between visual field size and electroretinogram amplitude in retinitis pigmentosa. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1996 Jul;37(8):1693-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8675413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>retinitis pigmentosa</keyword>
  <keyword>vitamin supplements</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinitis Pigmentosa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocopherols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocotrienols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>alpha-Tocopherol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinol palmitate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

