<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-31</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Manifest Glaucoma Trial (EMGT)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose is to compare the effect of immediate therapy to lower the intraocular
      pressure (IOP) versus late or no treatment on the progression of newly detected open-angle
      glaucoma, as measured by increasing visual field loss and/or optic disc changes.

      The secondary purposes are to determine the extent of IOP reduction attained by treatment, to
      explore factors that may influence glaucoma progression, and to describe the natural history
      of newly detected glaucoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Glaucoma is a common disease in older adults. All present treatment aims at reduction of the
      intraocular pressure, but indications for therapy are not well defined. Furthermore, it is
      unclear whether intraocular pressure influences the natural history of glaucoma. Against this
      background, the primary aim of the study is of central importance to patients with manifest
      and suspect glaucoma.

      Glaucoma has few subjective symptoms during a long period early in the disease, but damage is
      irreversible once it occurs. Early diagnosis and rapid detection of progression are of
      paramount importance in limiting this damage, whether through pressure reduction or in some
      other way. The effectiveness, if any, of lowering the intraocular pressure in glaucoma
      requires evaluation by controlled treatment trials.

      The Early Manifest Glaucoma Trial (EMGT) is the first large, controlled, randomized clinical
      trial to evaluate the effect of lowering the intraocular pressure on the progression of newly
      detected, open-angle glaucoma. This study will compare glaucoma progression in initially
      treated versus untreated patients with newly detected open-angle glaucoma and will allow
      quantification of the effect of immediate IOP-lowering treatment on progression during the
      followup period.

      The EMGT is a collaborative effort that involves a Clinical Center at the Department of
      Ophthalmology of Malmo University Hospital at the University of Lund, Sweden, and its
      Satellite Center in Helsingborg, Sweden; an independent Data Center at the Department of
      Preventive Medicine, University Medical Center at Stony Brook, New York; and a Disc
      Photography Reading Center at the Department of Ophthalmology in Lund at the University of
      Lund. The study was initiated with support from the Swedish Medical Research Council.

      Recruitment for the study has been completed. The 255 patients were identified by an
      extensive, population-based screening of successive age cohorts as well as by clinical
      referral. The diagnosis was confirmed through Humphrey perimetry at two postscreening visits
      to the Clinical Center or Satellite Center. Eligible patients who agreed to participate had
      two additional visits for collection of baseline data. They were randomized to treatment with
      the beta blocker Betaxolol and argon laser trabeculoplasty (treated group) or to no initial
      treatment (control group) with close followup of both groups.

      Patients are followed for a minimum of 4 years to assess the development of glaucoma
      progression. They are seen every 3 months to collect visual field, IOP, and other data. Disc
      photographs are taken every 6 months. Technicians and disc photograph graders are masked
      regarding treatment assignment. Additional followup visits are held to confirm visual field
      progression and IOP elevation (&gt;25 mm Hg in treated group, &gt;35 mm Hg in control group).
      Patients in the treated group receive Xalantan whenever IOP exceeds 25 mm Hg at more than one
      visit; patients in the control group will receive Xalantan whenever IOP reaches 35 mm Hg or
      higher during the trial. If IOP remains high, individualized treatment is given. All patients
      continue to be followed to monitor the development of end points and will be analyzed in
      their originally assigned groups.

      The study outcome is glaucoma progression, which is based on specific criteria derived from
      analyses of Humphrey visual fields and masked evaluations of disc photographs. The perimetric
      outcome is defined as statistically significant deterioration (p &lt; 0.05) of the same three or
      more test points in Pattern Deviation Change Probability Maps in three consecutive C30-2
      Humphrey fields. Optic disc progression is determined by the following:

        -  The presence of definite change (detected by comparison of followup photographs with
           baseline) by flicker chronoscopy in two followup photographs from the same visit, with
           independent confirmation by side-by-side gradings.

        -  Final confirmation of change toward progression, by flicker chronoscopy and by
           side-by-side gradings, at a different followup visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 1992</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Open-Angle Glaucoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Betaxolol</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Argon Laser Trabeculoplasty</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women between ages 50 and 80 years who have newly detected and untreated chronic
        open-angle glaucoma with repeatable visual field defects by Humphrey perimetry are eligible
        for inclusion.

        Exclusion criteria include the following: advanced visual field loss (MD less than or equal
        to 16 dB) or threat to fixation; mean IOP &gt; 30 mm Hg or any IOP &gt; 35 mm Hg in at least one
        eye; VA &lt; 0.5 in either eye; or any conditions precluding reliable fields or photos, use of
        study treatment, or 4-year followup.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, Helsingborg Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsingborg</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, Malmo University Hospital, University of Lund</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malmo</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2001</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Betaxolol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

