<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000123</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-22</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000123</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Berkeley Orthokeratology Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the relative efficacy of orthokeratology, primarily by assessment of changes in
      central corneal thickness, astigmatism, visual acuity, endothelial cell density, and corneal
      curvature.

      To evaluate the relative safety of orthokeratology, primarily by assessment of changes in
      central corneal thickness, astigmatism, visual acuity, endothelial cell density, induced
      corneal edema, and epithelial staining.

      To assess the duration of any orthokeratology treatment effect.

      To study the mechanisms by which refractive error and visual acuity changes occur, in
      particular the contribution that comes from changes in corneal curvature and shape.

      To determine whether there were any predisposing ocular factors that could be used to predict
      which subjects will experience changes or complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the early 1960s, a group of clinicians asserted that myopia could be reduced and possibly
      corrected by fitting specially designed contact lenses to induce corneal flattening and
      thereby reduce the refractive power of the eye. This technique, known as orthokeratology,
      required that the lenses be fitted and then changed progressively until vision becomes normal
      or nearly normal. Advocates of orthokeratology claimed that corneal changes could be induced
      in a predictable fashion, were often permanent, and occurred without causing any adverse
      effects to the cornea. Data on orthokeratology were generally limited, poorly documented, and
      did not address the issues of control or failure.

      The Berkeley Orthokeratology Study was a single center randomized, concurrently controlled,
      masked clinical trial. Corneal and visual changes in an orthokeratology treatment group were
      monitored and compared with those observed in a control group whose members wore contact
      lenses fitted in a standard clinical manner. Visual and ocular characteristics were monitored
      for 1.5 years.

      Eighty subjects were studied-40 in an orthokeratology group and 40 in a control group fitted
      with conventional hard contact lenses. The hard lenses chosen for this study were made of
      either polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) or a PMMA-silicone combination (Polycon). All subjects
      were initially fitted with PMMA lenses.

      The initial treatment and control lenses were selected according to protocol guidelines and
      then adjusted to achieve an &quot;optimal fit&quot; based on lens position, movement, and alignment as
      assessed by fluorescein study. At the outset, the treatment and control lenses differed in
      that the treatment lenses were on the average thicker and flatter and had a larger diameter.

      Following the dispensing visit, subjects progressed through three study phases. In the
      adaption phase (Phase A), subjects were examined weekly until they were adapted to 12 to 14
      hours of daily contact lens wear. The postadaptive phase (Phase B) consisted of monthly
      followup examinations for 1 year. The final phase (Phase C) consisted of a lens withdrawal
      segment and a postwearing segment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1978</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 1979</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Astigmatism</condition>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polymethyl Methacrylate-Silicone Contact Lenses</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polymethyl Methacrylate Contact Lenses</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Myopic volunteers, ages 20 to 35, who had not worn contact lenses were eligible to
        participate in the study if they were free of ocular disease, were in good physical health,
        and were not taking systemic medications that could have ocular side effects. In addition,
        eligibility was limited to persons with corneal curvature between 40.50 and 47.00 D
        (flatter keratometry reading), corrected visual acuity of 6/6 (20/20) or better in each
        eye, astigmatism less than 0.75 D, anisometropia less than 1 D, and myopia between 1 and 4
        D.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polse KA, Brand RJ. Contact lens effects on ametropia: a current example of the clinical trial. Am J Optom Physiol Opt. 1981 Apr;58(4):281-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7282852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brand RJ, Polse KA, Schwalbe JS. The Berkeley Orthokeratology Study, Part I: General conduct of the study. Am J Optom Physiol Opt. 1983 Mar;60(3):175-86.</citation>
    <PMID>6342407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polse KA, Brand RJ, Keener RJ, Schwalbe JS, Vastine DW. The Berkeley Orthokeratology Study, part III: safety. Am J Optom Physiol Opt. 1983 Apr;60(4):321-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6344645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polse KA, Brand RJ, Schwalbe JS, Vastine DW, Keener RJ. The Berkeley Orthokeratology Study, Part II: Efficacy and duration. Am J Optom Physiol Opt. 1983 Mar;60(3):187-98.</citation>
    <PMID>6342408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polse KA, Brand RJ, Vastine DW, Schwalbe JS. Corneal change accompanying orthokeratology. Plastic or elastic? Results of a randomized controlled clinical trial. Arch Ophthalmol. 1983 Dec;101(12):1873-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6360111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Astigmatism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polymethyl Methacrylate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

