<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of a Heparin-Coated Intraocular Lens in Uveitis</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the safety and efficacy of a heparin surface-modified intraocular lens in
      patients with uveitis undergoing cataract surgery.

      To evaluate the safety and efficacy of intraocular lens implantation in patients with severe
      uveitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with uveitis are at high risk for significant complications following cataract
      surgery with intraocular lens implantation. Complications may result from the surgery itself
      or may develop after surgery as a result of the intraocular lens. Complications related to
      intraocular lens implantation include iris adhesions to the intraocular lens, which can
      result in lens capture; cellular deposits on the surface of the lens that can obscure vision;
      and uveitis. Recent studies have identified giant cells on the anterior surface of
      intraocular lenses in some patients with uveitis, appearing to indicate an intraocular
      lens-induced inflammatory response. Some of these patients have required multiple YAG laser
      procedures to remove these deposits.

      Modification of the surface of the intraocular lens with a layer of heparin may provide a
      more biocompatible surface. Preclinical studies have shown a reduction in the degree of
      postoperative complications with the heparin surface-modified intraocular lens compared with
      an unmodified lens. Although retrospective case series have examined the use of heparin
      surface-modified intraocular lenses in patients with uveitis, a randomized, controlled
      clinical trial has not been performed.

      This is a randomized clinical trial examining the safety and efficacy of the heparin
      surface-modified intraocular lens in patients with uveitis. Eighty patients with a history of
      uveitis in an eye requiring cataract surgery will be randomized to receive a heparin
      surface-modified intraocular lens or the same model of intraocular lens without surface
      modification. The primary end point of the study will be the development of cellular deposits
      on the anterior surface of the intraocular lens 1 year after surgery. These cellular deposits
      will be assessed by a masked grader using standard photographs. Secondary end points will
      include visual acuity, intraocular inflammation, development of anterior and posterior
      synechiae, and corneal endothelial cell counts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 1994</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Heparin Surface-Modified Intraocular Lens</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Women and men 18 years or older with a documented history of uveitis in an eye requiring
        cataract surgery are eligible for the study. In all patients, the eye must be free of
        active inflammation for at least 3 months before surgery, with or without anti-inflammatory
        medications. Exclusion criteria include corneal pathology or hazy media that preclude
        evaluation of the intraocular lens, uncontrolled glaucoma, and diabetes mellitus. Monocular
        patients and patients who cannot be followed for at least 1 year are also excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892-1858</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heparin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

