<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000118</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000118</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ganciclovir Implant Study for Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the therapeutic efficacy of a sustained-release intraocular drug delivery system
      for ganciclovir therapy of cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis in patients with acquired
      immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CMV retinitis occurs in 20 to 30 percent of patients with AIDS and is the leading cause of
      visual loss in these patients. At present, ganciclovir and foscarnet are the only drugs that
      have been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for the treatment of CMV
      retinitis. The therapeutic regimen for each drug consists of a 2-week induction period
      followed by daily maintenance intravenous infusions. Unfortunately, CMV retinitis usually
      progresses despite daily maintenance therapy, and both drugs are associated with significant
      systemic toxicity that often limits their therapeutic usefulness. As an alternative to
      intravenous administration, direct intravitreal injections of ganciclovir have been studied
      and have been shown to be effective in delaying the progression of CMV retinitis. The short
      half-life of the drug, however, necessitates one to two intraocular injections a week to
      maintain therapeutic levels. Widespread adoption of this technique has been limited because
      of the logistical difficulties and inherent risks associated with numerous intravitreal
      injections.

      A drug delivery system capable of continuous delivery of ganciclovir into the vitreous cavity
      has been developed. The device consists of a 6-mg pellet of ganciclovir that is coated with a
      series of polymers with variable permeability to ganciclovir. The device is surgically
      implanted through the pars plana.

      Thirty eyes of 26 patients with unilateral non-sight-threatening CMV retinitis were randomly
      assigned to one of two groups: (1) immediate therapy with a device designed to release
      ganciclovir into the vitreous cavity a over approximately a 4-month period or (2) deferred
      treatment. In patients with bilateral non-sight-threatening CMV retinitis, one eye was
      randomly assigned to receive a ganciclovir implant with the other eye assigned to deferred
      treatment. (Note: The original trial design included a third randomized arm using a 2 ug/hour
      device. This arm was dropped for logistical reasons after enrolling two patients.)

      Patients assigned to immediate treatment underwent surgery to implant the ganciclovir device
      within 48 hours of enrollment and baseline photographs. Postoperatively, patients were
      evaluated the next day, weekly for 2 weeks, and then every 2 weeks until progression of CMV
      retinitis occurred. At each examination, in both eyes, visual acuity with current correction
      and best correction was determined using Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study eye
      charts; intraocular pressure was determined; evidence of inflammation or cataract was
      evaluated; and all retinal findings were documented. Any adverse event considered even
      possibly related to the device or to the implantation procedure was documented. Standardized
      nine-field fundus photographs were taken at each 2-week visit. The ganciclovir implant was
      exchanged at 32 weeks or earlier if progression of CMV retinitis occurred.

      The primary end point was time to CMV retinitis progression, defined as the time (days) from
      initiating therapy until the advancement of 750-um over a 750 um front of any border of any
      lesion was observed. Standardized nine-field photographs were taken at 2-week intervals and
      analyzed in a masked fashion by the Fundus Photograph Reading Center to determine evidence of
      CMV retinitis progression.

      Secondary end points included time to development of CMV retinitis in the contralateral eye,
      time to development of visceral CMV, and time to death.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1992</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 1993</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sustained-Release Intraocular Drug Delivery System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        All patients must have had AIDS as defined by the Centers for Disease Control and
        Prevention and non-sight-threatening CMV retinitis Patients could not have been previously
        treated with systemic ganciclovir or foscarnet and must not have had evidence of other
        organ involvement with CMV. Patients must have had an absolute neutrophil count (ANC)
        greater than 1,000 cells/mL and a platelet count greater than 25,000/mm3
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/clinicalalerts/alert-soca-fgcrt.asp</url>
    <description>Clinical Alert To Physicians And Others Who Treat Patients With AIDS</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/gipressrelease.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Eye Implant Effective in Treating CMV Retinitis</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin DF, Parks DJ, Mellow SD, Ferris FL, Walton RC, Remaley NA, Chew EY, Ashton P, Davis MD, Nussenblatt RB. Treatment of cytomegalovirus retinitis with an intraocular sustained-release ganciclovir implant. A randomized controlled clinical trial. Arch Ophthalmol. 1994 Dec;112(12):1531-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7993207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

