<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000121</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-20</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000121</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Prism Adaptation Study (PAS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether the preoperative use of prisms in eyeglasses can improve the outcome of
      surgery for acquired esotropia, a type of strabismus.

      To determine whether patients who respond to prism adaptation by developing a new stable
      angle of -deviation have a better surgical result than do patients who do not respond to
      prism adaptation.

      To determine whether patients who respond to prism adaptation are more accurately corrected
      by operating for the prism-adapted angle or the original angle of deviation.

      To determine the usefulness of certain input variables (e.g., age at the time of surgery,
      size of the deviation, visual acuity, binocular function, refractive error) in predicting
      which patients are more likely to benefit from prism adaptation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acquired esotropia (crossed eyes that develop after a child reaches the age of 6 months)
      accounts for 25 percent of all patients with misaligned eyes. Surgery to correct esotropia is
      done primarily to attain functional use of the two eyes together. The cosmetic aspect of the
      surgery is secondary. In 40 to 50 percent of cases, more than one operation is needed to
      accomplish the primary goal, and in some cases even three and four operations are needed.

      Preliminary studies from two eye care centers reported that the use of prisms on eyeglasses
      for about a month before surgery led to good results after a single operation in more than 90
      percent of patients. These uncontrolled preliminary studies pointed to the need for a
      multicenter, randomized, controlled clinical trial designed to prove or disprove
      scientifically the beneficial effect of prisms.

      The Prism Adaptation Study was a double randomization trial involving 286 patients.
      Three-fifths of the patients were randomly selected for prism adaptation before surgery. Of
      the patients who responded to the prisms, one-half were randomly selected to have surgery
      based on the amount of prism required to stabilize the deviation, and the other half had
      surgery based on the amount of esotropia originally measured. Patients who did not respond to
      the prisms also had surgery based on the amount of esotropia measured, as did the two-fifths
      of the patients who did not undergo prism adaptation.

      Patients were examined postoperatively at 1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, and 1 year. An
      independent examiner, masked to the treatment assignment, evaluated the patient at the
      6-month followup. The results were analyzed to determine whether the outcome was better in
      patients who underwent prism adaptation or in those who underwent conventional treatment.
      Because the examiner did not know what type of treatment a patient had received, he or she
      would have no bias in evaluating the results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1984</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1989</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Esotropia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prisms in Eyeglasses</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        An eligible male or female must have been age 3 years or older (adults were included) and
        must have had esotropia that occurred at age 6 months or older, with no history of previous
        eye muscle surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efficacy of prism adaptation in the surgical management of acquired esotropia. Prism Adaptation Study Research Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1990 Sep;108(9):1248-56.</citation>
    <PMID>2100986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Repka MX, Connett JE, Scott WE. The one-year surgical outcome after prism adaptation for the management of acquired esotropia. Ophthalmology. 1996 Jun;103(6):922-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8643248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>strabismus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esotropia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

