<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000149</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-50</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000149</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study (CIGTS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the long-term effect of treating newly diagnosed open-angle glaucoma with standard
      medical treatment versus filtration surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent studies have challenged the conventional wisdom of treating all newly diagnosed
      open-angle glaucoma (OAG) with eyedrops; rather, these studies suggest that more effective
      control of glaucomatous damage can be obtained by immediate filtration surgery. In addition,
      increased attention to the impact of therapy on health-related quality of life has added
      another consideration in deciding upon appropriate treatment of such patients.

      The Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study (CIGTS), a randomized, controlled clinical
      trial, is being conducted to determine whether patients with newly diagnosed OAG are best
      managed by the conventional approach of topical pharmacologic agents or by immediate
      filtration surgery. Eligible patients were randomized to receive either a stepped medication
      treatment regimen or filtration surgery to control their OAG. Sample size requirements
      indicated that 300 patients were needed for each treatment approach; a total of 607 patients
      were ultimately recruited for the CIGTS.

      Patients randomized to the medication treatment arm are receiving a stepped regimen of
      topical medications, beginning with a single agent (typically a beta blocker), with
      additional medications added upon documented lack of intraocular pressure control or evidence
      of progressive visual field loss. If medications fail to control the patient's OAG, a series
      of treatment steps begin with argon laser trabeculoplasty and conclude with trabeculectomy.

      In the surgical treatment arm, patients underwent immediate trabeculectomy and, with
      documented failure, proceed to argon laser trabeculectomy, then conclude with medications.
      Patients, rather than eyes, are randomized to the two treatment arms; if both eyes are
      eligible for treatment, the treatment course for both eyes is the same and was determined in
      the randomization.

      Following randomization, participating community ophthalmologists affiliated with the study
      have been allowed to manage the medical and surgical care of study patients. However, all
      patients are seen at the Clinical Centers for standardized followup examinations at 3 and 6
      months after treatment and every 6 months thereafter; in addition, patients randomized to the
      surgical arm will receive, at a minimum, postsurgical followup at 1 day, 1 week, and 1 month.
      At the Clinical Center visits, examination of the eye(s) includes evaluation of visual
      acuity, visual field, and intraocular pressure. The results of these tests determine whether
      treatment should be changed. In addition, before and at regular intervals after treatment,
      patients are being interviewed by telephone to assess their health-related quality of life. A
      questionnaire that includes the Sickness Impact Profile, Visual Activities Questionnaire, and
      other components is being used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 1993</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Open-Angle Glaucoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Beta Blocker</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trabeculectomy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Argon Laser Trabeculoplasty</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients must be at least 25 years old with an intraocular pressure of 20 mm Hg or greater
        and evidence of optic nerve damage and/or visual field loss in one or both eyes. The ocular
        findings must exclude causes of glaucoma other than primary open-angle glaucoma, pigmentary
        glaucoma, or pseudoexfoliation glaucoma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janz N; Wren PA; CIGTS Study Group; Implementing quality of life in a clinical trial, in Anderson DR, Drance SM (eds)., The Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study. Encounters in Glaucoma Research 3: How to Ascertain Progression and Outcome, 1996:45-62</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lichter PR; Mills RP; CIGTS Study Group; Quality of life study - determination of progression, in Anderson DR, Drance SM (eds)., Encounters in Glaucoma Research 3: How to Ascertain Progression and Outcome, Amsterdam, Kugler Publications, 1996:149-163</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mills RP, Janz NK, Wren PA, Guire KE. Correlation of visual field with quality-of-life measures at diagnosis in the Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study (CIGTS). J Glaucoma. 2001 Jun;10(3):192-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11442181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lichter PR, Musch DC, Gillespie BW, Guire KE, Janz NK, Wren PA, Mills RP; CIGTS Study Group. Interim clinical outcomes in the Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study comparing initial treatment randomized to medications or surgery. Ophthalmology. 2001 Nov;108(11):1943-53.</citation>
    <PMID>11713061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janz NK, Wren PA, Lichter PR, Musch DC, Gillespie BW, Guire KE, Mills RP; CIGTS Study Group. The Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study: interim quality of life findings after initial medical or surgical treatment of glaucoma. Ophthalmology. 2001 Nov;108(11):1954-65.</citation>
    <PMID>11713062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janz NK, Wren PA, Lichter PR, Musch DC, Gillespie BW, Guire KE. Quality of life in newly diagnosed glaucoma patients : The Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study. Ophthalmology. 2001 May;108(5):887-97; discussion 898.</citation>
    <PMID>11320018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Musch DC, Lichter PR, Guire KE, Standardi CL. The Collaborative Initial Glaucoma Treatment Study: study design, methods, and baseline characteristics of enrolled patients. Ophthalmology. 1999 Apr;106(4):653-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10201583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenergic beta-Antagonists</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

