<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IA0011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>3U01AG010483-08S2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Memory Impairment Study (Mild Cognitive Impairment Study)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial of Vitamin E and Donepezil HCL (Aricept) to Delay Clinical Progression From Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) to Alzheimer's Disease (AD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study (ADCS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The National Institute on Aging (NIA) is launching a nationwide treatment study targeting
      individuals with mild cognitive impairment (MCI), a condition characterized by a memory
      deficit, but not dementia. An NIA-funded study recently confirmed that MCI is different from
      both dementia and normal age-related changes in memory. Accurate and early evaluation and
      treatment of MCI individuals might prevent further cognitive decline, including development
      of Alzheimer's disease (AD).

      The Memory Impairment Study is the first such AD prevention clinical trial carried out by
      NIH, and will be conducted at 65-80 medical research institutions located in the United
      States and Canada. This study will test the usefulness of two drugs to slow or stop the
      conversion from MCI to AD. The trial will evaluate placebo, vitamin E, and donepezil, an
      investigational agent approved by the Food and Drug Administration for another use. Vitamin E
      (alpha-tocopherol) is thought to have antioxidant properties, and was shown in a 1997 study
      to delay important dementia milestones, such as patients' institutionalization or progression
      to severe dementia, by about seven months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial will be a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo- controlled,
      parallel-group study of vitamin E and donepezil in 720 subjects with mild cognitive
      impairment (MCI). Subjects will be randomized to one of three treatment groups (240 subjects
      per treatment group): 1) Placebo vitamin E and placebo donepezil plus a multivitamin daily.
      2) Vitamin E (2,000 I) and placebo donepezil plus a multivitamin daily.3) Donepezil (10 mg)
      and placebo vitamin E plus a multivitamin daily.

      The study will be conducted over three years, with clinical evaluations every 3 months for
      the first 6 months and then every 6 months. Subjects randomized to donepezil will start a
      dose of 5 mg daily. Donepezil will be increased to 10 mg after six weeks. Subjects randomized
      to vitamin E will start at 1,000 I daily. The dose of Vitamin E will be increased to 2,000 I
      after six weeks. There will be a 12-month recruitment period. The primary endpoint will be
      time to development of Probable or Possible AD according to NINCDS-ADRDA criteria. Upon
      determination of a clinical diagnosis of AD, documentation will be sent to the ADCS
      Coordinating Center and forwarded to the Central Review Committee for verification. Upon
      verification, of conversion to diagnosis of AD, subjects will stop taking the donepezil study
      medication or its corresponding placebo, without breaking the blind, and will be offered open
      label donepezil at a scheduled visit one month after the prior diagnostic visit. Donepezil
      will be offered to subjects who convert to AD until the subject completes three years from
      the baseline visit. Based on an estimated incidence of AD of 15% per year, the study has 85%
      power to detect a 33% or greater reduction in conversion to AD over 3 years. Secondary
      outcome measures will include change on the Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale (ADAS-COG),
      the Neuropsychological Battery, the Mini-Mental State Exam (MMSE), Clinical Dementia Rating
      Scale (CDR), the Global Deterioration Scale (GDS), ADCS- Activities of Daily Living Inventory
      (ADCS-ADL), a Pharmacoeconomics scale, and a Quality of Life scale. Compliance will be
      monitored through the measurement of alpha-tocopherol levels and pill counts at each visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Donepezil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin E</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Memory complaints and memory difficulties which are verified by an informant.

          -  Abnormal memory function documented by scoring below the education adjusted cutoff on
             the Logical Memory II subscale (Delayed Paragraph Recall) from the Wechsler Memory
             Scale - Revised (the maximum score is 25): a) less than or equal to 8 for 16 or more
             years of education, b) less than or equal to 4 for 8-15 years of education, c) less
             than or equal to 2 for 0-7 years of education.

          -  Mini-Mental Exam score between 24 and 30 (inclusive) (Exceptions may be made for
             subjects with less than 8 years of education at the discretion of the project
             director.).

          -  Clinical Dementia Rating = 0.5. Memory Box score must be at least 0.5.

          -  General cognition and functional performance sufficiently preserved such that a
             diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease cannot be made by the site physician at the time of
             the screening visit.

          -  No significant cerebrovascular disease: Modified Hachinski score of less than or equal
             to 4.

          -  Age between 55 and 90 (inclusive).

          -  Permitted medications stable for at least 1 month prior to screening. In particular:
             a) Subjects may take stable doses of antidepressants lacking significant
             anticholinergic side effects (if they are not currently depressed and do not have a
             history of major depression within the past 2 years). b) Estrogen replacement therapy
             is permissible. c) Ginkgo biloba is permissible, but discouraged.

          -  Hamilton Depression rating scale score of less than or equal to 12 on the 17-item
             scale.

          -  Informant is available who has frequent contact with the subject (e.g. an average of
             10 hours per week or more), agrees to monitor administration of study drug, observe
             for adverse events, and accompany the subject to all clinic visits for the duration of
             the protocol.

          -  CT or MRI scans within 12 months prior to screening without evidence of infection,
             infarction, or other focal lesions and without clinical symptoms suggestive of
             intervening neurological disease. A lacune in a non-critical brain area which is not
             believed to contribute to the subject's cognitive impairment is permissible.

          -  Adequate visual and auditory acuity to allow neuropsychological testing.

          -  Good general health with no additional diseases expected to interfere with the study.

          -  Normal B12, RPR, and Thyroid Function Tests or without any clinically significant
             abnormalities that would be expected to interfere with the study.

          -  ECG without clinically significant abnormalities that would be expected to interfere
             with the study.

          -  Subject is not pregnant, lactating, or of childbearing potential (i.e. women must be
             two years post-menopausal or surgically sterile).

          -  Agreement not to take other vitamin supplements (including Vitamin E), multivitamins,
             other than those provided by the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any significant neurologic disease other than suspected incipient Alzheimer's disease,
             such as Parkinson's disease, multi-infarct dementia, Huntington's disease, normal
             pressure hydrocephalus, brain tumor, progressive supranuclear palsy, seizure disorder,
             subdural hematoma, multiple sclerosis, or history of significant head trauma followed
             by persistent neurologic defaults or known structural brain abnormalities.

          -  Major depression or another major psychiatric disorder as described in DSM IV within
             the past 2 years.

          -  Psychotic features, agitation or behavioral problems within the last 3 months which
             could lead to difficulty complying with the protocol.

          -  History of alcohol or substance abuse or dependence within the past 2 years (DSM IV
             criteria).

          -  History of schizophrenia (DSM IV criteria).

          -  Any significant systemic illness or unstable medical condition which could lead to
             difficulty complying with the protocol including: a) History of systemic cancer within
             the last 5 years (non-metastatic skin cancers are acceptable). b) History of
             myocardial infarction within the past year or unstable or severe cardiovascular
             disease including angina or CHF with symptoms at rest. c) Clinically significant
             obstructive pulmonary disease or asthma. d) Clinically significant and unstable
             gastrointestinal disorder such as ulcer disease or a history of active or occult
             gastrointestinal bleeding within two years. e) Clinically significant laboratory test
             abnormalities on the battery of screening tests (hematology, prothrombin time,
             chemistry, urinalysis, ECG). f) Insulin-requiring diabetes or uncontrolled diabetes
             mellitus. g) Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic BP greater than 170 or diastolic
             greater than 100). h) History of clinically significant liver disease, coagulopathy,
             or vitamin K deficiency within the past 2 years.

          -  Medications a) Use of centrally active beta-blockers, narcotics, methyldopa and
             clonidine within 4 weeks prior to screening. b) Use of anti-Parkinsonian medications
             (e.g. Sinemet, amantadine, bromocriptine, pergolide and selegiline) within 2 months
             prior to screening. c) Use of neuroleptics or narcotic analgesics within 4 weeks prior
             to screening. d) Use of long-acting benzodiazepines or barbituates within 4 weeks
             prior to screening. e) Use of short-acting anxiolytics or sedative hypnotics more
             frequently than 2 times per week within 4 weeks prior to screening (note: sedative
             agents should not be used within 72 hours of screening).

             f) Initiation or change in dose of an antidepressant lacking significant cholinergic
             side effects within the 4 weeks prior to screening (use of stable doses of
             antidepressants for at least 4 weeks prior to screening is acceptable). g) Use of
             systemic corticosteroids within 3 months prior to screening. h) Medications with
             significant cholinergic or anticholinergic side effects (e.g. pyridostigmine,
             tricyclic antidepressants, meclizine, and oxybutynin) within 4 weeks prior to
             screening. i) Use of anti-convulsants (e.g. Phenytoin, Phenobarbital, Carbamazepine)
             within 2 months prior to screening. j) Use of warfarin (Coumadin) within 4 weeks prior
             to screening.

          -  Vitamin Supplements a) Use of vitamin supplements other than standard multivitamin
             included as part of the treatment intervention used in this protocol within 2 weeks
             prior to screening.

          -  Any prior use of any FDA approved medications for the treatment of Alzheimer's disease
             (e.g. tacrine, donepezil, or other newly approved medications).

          -  Use of any investigational drugs within 30 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer,
             prior to screening.

          -  Subjects who, in the investigator's opinion, will not comply with study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leon Thal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barrow Neurological Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>857245023</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Irvine Institute for Brain Aging and Dementia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Irvine</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92697-4285</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095-1769</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>East Bay Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Martinez</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94553</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sutter Institute for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95816</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Affiliated Research Instiute</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92018</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093-0949</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baumel-Eisner Neuromedical Institute, Boca Raton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boca Raton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33486</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baumel-Eisner Neuromedical Institute, Ft. Lauderdale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33321</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Jacksonville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32225</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wein Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baumel-Eisner Neuromedical Institute, MiamiBeach</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33154</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Charlotte</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33952</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Premiere Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Palm Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30329</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Augusta VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush Presbyterian St. Luke's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southern Illinois University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-5111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66160</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536-0230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55901-0144</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nevada</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memory Disorders Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lakehurst</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08733</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princeton Biomedical Research, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Princeton</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08540</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ClinSearch, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Summit</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princeton Biomedical - Toms River</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toms River</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08755</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alzheimer's Research Corp.</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Long Branch</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07764</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ. of New Mexico</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>89108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maimonides Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nathan S. Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orangeburg</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10962</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14620</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Stony Brook</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stony Brook</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11794-8121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Burke Medical Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>White Plains</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals of Cleveland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44120-1013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health Sciences University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97201-3098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MCP Hahnemann</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19129</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pawtucket</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02860</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29406</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37212-8646</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southwestern Vermont Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bennington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neuroscience Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Marshfield Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marshfield</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>54449</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Calgary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 4N1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of British Columbia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6T 2B5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fredericton Medical Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fredericton</city>
        <state>New Brunswick</state>
        <zip>E3B 6H5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geriatric Medicine Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H 2E1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 4V2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Elizabeth Bruyere Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1N 5C8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Science Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jewish General Hospital Memory Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T 1E2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McGill Centre for Studies in Aging</name>
      <address>
        <city>Verdun</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4H 1R3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://adcs.ucsd.edu</url>
    <description>More information about the study from the Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study site at the University of California at San Diego.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rogers SL, Farlow MR, Doody RS, Mohs R, Friedhoff LT. A 24-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of donepezil in patients with Alzheimer's disease. Donepezil Study Group. Neurology. 1998 Jan;50(1):136-45.</citation>
    <PMID>9443470</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petersen RC, Smith GE, Waring SC, Ivnik RJ, Kokmen E, Tangelos EG. Aging, memory, and mild cognitive impairment. Int Psychogeriatr. 1997;9 Suppl 1:65-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9447429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubin EH, Morris JC, Grant EA, Vendegna T. Very mild senile dementia of the Alzheimer type. I. Clinical assessment. Arch Neurol. 1989 Apr;46(4):379-82.</citation>
    <PMID>2650663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Grundman M, Petersen RC, Ferris SH, Thomas RG, Aisen PS, Bennett DA, Foster NL, Jack CR Jr, Galasko DR, Doody R, Kaye J, Sano M, Mohs R, Gauthier S, Kim HT, Jin S, Schultz AN, Schafer K, Mulnard R, van Dyck CH, Mintzer J, Zamrini EY, Cahn-Weiner D, Thal LJ; Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study. Mild cognitive impairment can be distinguished from Alzheimer disease and normal aging for clinical trials. Arch Neurol. 2004 Jan;61(1):59-66.</citation>
    <PMID>14732621</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 1, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Mild cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Memory</keyword>
  <keyword>Donepezil</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin E</keyword>
  <keyword>Antioxidants</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholinergic agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholinesterase inhibitors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocopherols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocotrienols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>alpha-Tocopherol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Donepezil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

