<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000113</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-9</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U10EY011756</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000113</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Correction of Myopia Evaluation Trial (COMET)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Correction of Myopia Evaluation Trial (COMET)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stony Brook University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stony Brook University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate whether progressive addition lenses (PALs) slow the rate of progression of
      juvenile-onset myopia (nearsightedness) when compared with single vision lenses, as measured
      by cycloplegic autorefraction. An additional outcome measure is axial length, as measured by
      A-scan ultrasonography.

      To describe the natural history of juvenile-onset myopia in a group of children receiving
      conventional treatment (single vision lenses).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Myopia (nearsightedness) is an important public health problem, which entails substantial
      societal and personal costs. It is highly prevalent in our society and even more frequent in
      Asian countries; furthermore, its prevalence may be increasing over time. High myopia
      contributes to significant loss of vision and blindness. At present, the mechanisms involved
      in the etiology of myopia are unclear, and there is no way to prevent the condition. Current
      methods of correction require lifelong use of lenses or surgical treatment, which is
      expensive and may lead to complications. The rationale for this trial, the Correction of
      Myopia Evaluation Trial (COMET), arises from the convergence of research involving (1) the
      link between accommodation and myopia in children and (2) animal models of myopia showing the
      important role of the visual environment in eye growth. A contribution of this research is
      that blur is a critical component in the development of myopia. The primary aim of COMET, to
      evaluate the efficacy of progressive addition lenses, a noninvasive intervention, in slowing
      the progression of myopia, follows from this line of reasoning. These lenses should provide
      clear visual input over a range of viewing distances without focusing effort by the child.
      The comparison of myopia progression in children treated with PALs versus single vision
      lenses will allow the quantification of the effect of PALs on myopia progression during the
      followup period.

      The COMET is a multicenter, randomized, double-masked clinical trial to evaluate whether PALs
      slow the progression of juvenile-onset myopia as compared with single vision lenses. The
      study is a collaborative effort that involves a Study Chair at the New England College of
      Optometry; four clinical centers at colleges of optometry in Boston, Birmingham,
      Philadelphia, and Houston; and a Coordinating Center at the State University of New York at
      Stony Brook.

      The sample size goal, 450 children with myopia in both eyes who met specific inclusion and
      exclusion criteria, was attained with the enrollment of 469 children in one year. Children
      were identified from school screenings, clinic records, and referrals from local
      practitioners. Eligible children were randomly assigned to receive progressive addition or
      single vision lenses. Participating children are being examined at 6-month intervals
      following baseline, for at least 3 years, to measure changes in refractive error and to
      update prescriptions, according to a specified protocol. A dilated examination to evaluate
      the study outcome measures is performed at the annual study visits. A standardized, common
      protocol is used at all centers.

      The primary outcome of the study is progression of myopia, defined as the magnitude of the
      change relative to baseline in spherical equivalent refraction, determined by cycloplegic
      autorefraction. The secondary outcome of the study is axial length measured by A-scan
      ultrasonography.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2001</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression of myopia, determined by cycloplegic autorefraction</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Axial length measured by A-scan ultrasonography</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">469</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Addition Lenses (PALs)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Vision Lenses</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progressive Addition Lenses</intervention_name>
    <description>Varilux comfort with +2.00 addition</description>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Addition Lenses (PALs)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>single vision lenses</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Single Vision Lenses</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Children between the ages of 6 and 12 years with myopia in both eyes (defined as spherical
        equivalent between -1.25 D and -4.50 D in each eye as measured by cycloplegic
        autorefraction), astigmatism less than or equal to 1.50 D, and no anisometropia (defined as
        a difference in spherical equivalent between the two eyes greater than 1.0 D) are eligible
        for inclusion. Exclusion criteria include visual acuity greater than 20/25, strabismus, use
        of contact lenses, birth weight less than 1,250 grams, use of bifocal or progressive
        addition lenses, or any conditions precluding adherence to the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jane Gwiazda, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>New England College of Optometry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leslie Hyman, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Stony Brook Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama-Birmingham, School of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294-0010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New England College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennsylvania College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19141-3399</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Houston, College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77204-6052</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/health/clinicalstudies/</url>
    <description>NEI Clinical Studies Database</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gwiazda J, Hyman L, Hussein M, Everett D, Norton TT, Kurtz D, Leske MC, Manny R, Marsh-Tootle W, Scheiman M. A randomized clinical trial of progressive addition lenses versus single vision lenses on the progression of myopia in children. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2003 Apr;44(4):1492-500.</citation>
    <PMID>12657584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gwiazda JE, Hyman L, Norton TT, Hussein ME, Marsh-Tootle W, Manny R, Wang Y, Everett D; COMET Grouup. Accommodation and related risk factors associated with myopia progression and their interaction with treatment in COMET children. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2004 Jul;45(7):2143-51.</citation>
    <PMID>15223788</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hyman L, Gwiazda J, Hussein M, Norton TT, Wang Y, Marsh-Tootle W, Everett D. Relationship of age, sex, and ethnicity with myopia progression and axial elongation in the correction of myopia evaluation trial. Arch Ophthalmol. 2005 Jul;123(7):977-87.</citation>
    <PMID>16009841</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>myopia</keyword>
  <keyword>nearsightedness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

