<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-36</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies (CCTS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether histocompatibility matching of corneal transplant donors and recipients
      can reduce the incidence of graft rejection in high-risk patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 20 percent of corneal transplant patients, about 6,000 per year, face donor
      tissue rejection at rates of up to 60 percent because of corneal vascularization or prior
      graft rejection. Histocompatibility antigen matching and/or crossmatching may have offered
      these patients an improved chance for successful outcome.

      The Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies Group conducted two controlled,
      double-masked studies addressing distinct scientific questions about donor-recipient
      histocompatibility matching. The Crossmatch Study was a randomized study assessing the
      effectiveness of crossmatching in preventing graft rejection among high-risk patients with
      lymphocytotoxic antibodies. The Antigen Matching Study was a prospective, double-masked,
      observational study of the effectiveness of HLA-A, -B, and -DR donor-recipient matching in
      high-risk patients who had no lymphocytotoxic antibodies.

      Six clinical centers recruited high-risk patients and collaborated with their local eye
      banking and organ procurement agencies in procuring donor corneal tissue. For each of the two
      studies, a total of 400 patients were sought. Blood samples from each enrolled patient were
      sent to the local CCTS tissue typing laboratory for HLA typing, and serum samples were sent
      to the Central Laboratory to be screened for preformed lymphocytotoxic antibodies. Depending
      on the results of the testing, patients were entered into the Crossmatch Study or the Antigen
      Matching Study.

      As corneal donors became available, donor blood samples were HLA typed at the local
      laboratories and crossmatched against all CCTS patients who awaited transplantation. Results
      of the testing were entered in a national, 24-hour computerized allocation system operated by
      the United Network for Organ Sharing (UNOS). Patients in the Crossmatch Study received a
      cornea from either a positively crossmatched donor or a negatively crossmatched donor.
      Patients in the Antigen Matching Study received a cornea with 0 to 6 matched antigens.

      Transplant patients were followed intensively during the first months after surgery. The
      number of clinic visits was tapered to 2 during the third and final year of followup,
      resulting in a total of 17 postoperative visits. Irreversible failure of the corneal
      allograft due to all causes was the primary outcome variable in both studies. Allograft
      reaction episodes, irreversible failure due to rejection, and visual acuity were secondary
      outcome variables.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1986</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1989</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Corneal Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Graft Rejection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Histocompatibility Matching</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Males and females age 10 years or older with two to four quadrants of corneal stroma
        vascularization or a history of allograft rejection in the eye considered for surgery were
        eligible for both studies in the CCTS.

        Patients must have been willing to participate in 3 years of followup. No one was eligible
        for the CCTS who had a condition that would greatly increase the risk of nonrejection graft
        failure, such as xerophthalmia or severe exposure keratopathy. Also excluded were patients
        with systemic diseases or with medication usage that might alter their immune response.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/101492.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Patient/Donor Blood Type Matching Improves Corneal Transplantation Outcome</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stark WJ, Stulting RD, Thoft R. HLA matching and corneal transplantation. N Engl J Med. 1987 Dec 3;317(23):1476-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3317044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein PK; Stark WJ; Maguire MG; Stulting RD; Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Research Group; Donor-recipient crossmatching and typing to avoid corneal allograft rejection, in Cavanaugh HD (ed)., The Cornea: The World Congress on the Cornea III, New York, Raven Press, 1988:395-398</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stark WJ, Stulting RD, Meyer RF, Foulks GN, Smith RE, Chandler JW, Maguire MG, Bias WB. Sharing tissue typing information from the collaborative corneal transplantation studies. Arch Ophthalmol. 1989 May;107(5):633.</citation>
    <PMID>2655566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The collaborative corneal transplantation studies (CCTS). Effectiveness of histocompatibility matching in high-risk corneal transplantation. The Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies Research Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1992 Oct;110(10):1392-403.</citation>
    <PMID>1417537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDonnell PJ, Enger C, Stark WJ, Stulting RD. Corneal thickness changes after high-risk penetrating keratoplasty. Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Study Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1993 Oct;111(10):1374-81.</citation>
    <PMID>8216018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fink N, Stark WJ, Maguire MG, Stulting D, Meyer R, Foulks G, Smith RE, Rapoza P. Effectiveness of histocompatibility matching in high-risk corneal transplantation: a summary of results from the Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies. Cesk Oftalmol. 1994 Feb;50(1):3-12.</citation>
    <PMID>8137435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maguire MG, Stark WJ, Gottsch JD, Stulting RD, Sugar A, Fink NE, Schwartz A. Risk factors for corneal graft failure and rejection in the collaborative corneal transplantation studies. Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies Research Group. Ophthalmology. 1994 Sep;101(9):1536-47.</citation>
    <PMID>8090456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hahn AB, Foulks GN, Enger C, Fink N, Stark WJ, Hopkins KA, Sanfilippo F. The association of lymphocytotoxic antibodies with corneal allograft rejection in high risk patients. The Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies Research Group. Transplantation. 1995 Jan 15;59(1):21-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7839424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamp MT, Fink NE, Enger C, Maguire MG, Stark WJ, Stulting RD. Patient-reported symptoms associated with graft reactions in high-risk patients in the collaborative corneal transplantation studies. Collaborative Corneal Transplantation Studies Research Group. Cornea. 1995 Jan;14(1):43-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7712736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

