<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000144</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-43</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000144</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT) Glaucoma Laser Trial Followup Study (GLTFS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the safety and long-term efficacy of argon laser treatment of the trabecular
      meshwork with standard medical treatment for primary open-angle glaucoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the last decade, argon laser trabeculoplasty (ALT) has often been used instead of
      surgery as the treatment of choice in cases of open-angle glaucoma that could not be
      controlled by drugs. ALT treatment consists of tiny laser burns evenly spaced around the
      trabecular meshwork. It sometimes has been found to be effective in controlling glaucoma,
      although many eyes still require some medical treatment.

      The Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT), a randomized, controlled clinical trial, was conducted to
      determine whether ALT is effective in patients with newly diagnosed, primary, open-angle
      glaucoma. Each of the 271 patients in the trial received argon laser treatment in one eye and
      standard topical medication in the other eye. The eye to be started on medicine and the eye
      that would get the laser treatment were randomly selected. The Glaucoma Laser Trial Followup
      Study was a followup study of 203 of the 271 patients who enrolled in the Glaucoma Laser
      Trial. By the close of the Glaucoma Laser Trial Followup Study, median duration of followup
      since diagnosis of primary, open-angle glaucoma was 7 years (maximum, 9 years).

      The argon laser treatment was done in two sessions 1 month apart, with one-half of the
      trabecular meshwork treated with 45 to 55 laser burns in each session. Patients were seen for
      a followup visit 3 months after the first laser treatment and every 3 months thereafter for a
      period of at least 2 years. At each visit, examination of the eyes included a check of
      intraocular pressure and visual acuity. Visual field examinations were performed 3, 6, and 12
      months after randomization and annually thereafter. Disc stereo photographs were taken 6 and
      12 months after randomization and annually thereafter.

      The results of these examinations determined whether treatment should be changed. If the
      pressure in either eye had not been reduced to the desired level, the physician changed the
      medication in the eye treated with drops or started the use of drops in the laser-treated eye
      according to a standardized procedure being used in the trial. If intraocular pressure was
      still not successfully reduced, surgery or further laser treatment may have been required.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1984</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Open-Angle Glaucoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Argon Laser Treatment</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        At the time of recruitment, patients had to be at least 35 years old with an intraocular
        pressure of at least 22 mm Hg or greater in each eye and evidence of optic nerve damage in
        at least one eye.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/gltpressrelease.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Laser Surgery Is Safe And Effective First Treatment For Glaucoma</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/glt-1pressrelease.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Laser Therapy Show Promise As Alternative to Glaucoma Drugs</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT). 2. Results of argon laser trabeculoplasty versus topical medicines. The Glaucoma Laser Trial Research Group. Ophthalmology. 1990 Nov;97(11):1403-13.</citation>
    <PMID>2255512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT): 3. Design and methods. Glaucoma Laser Trial Research Group. Control Clin Trials. 1991 Aug;12(4):504-24.</citation>
    <PMID>1657527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial: 4. Contralateral effects of timolol on the intraocular pressure of eyes treated with ALT. GLT Research Group. Ophthalmic Surg. 1991 Jun;22(6):324-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1896168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT): 5. Subgroup differences at enrollment. Glaucoma Laser Trial Research Group. Ophthalmic Surg. 1993 Apr;24(4):232-40.</citation>
    <PMID>8321504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT): 6. Treatment group differences in visual field changes. Glaucoma Laser Trial Research Group. Am J Ophthalmol. 1995 Jul;120(1):10-22.</citation>
    <PMID>7611312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial (GLT) and glaucoma laser trial follow-up study: 7. Results. Glaucoma Laser Trial Research Group. Am J Ophthalmol. 1995 Dec;120(6):718-31.</citation>
    <PMID>8540545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Glaucoma Laser Trial. I. Acute effects of argon laser trabeculoplasty on intraocular pressure. Glaucoma Laser Trial Research Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1989 Aug;107(8):1135-42.</citation>
    <PMID>2667508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 5, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

