<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000140</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-39</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000140</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Silicone Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare, through a randomized, multicenter surgical trial, the postoperative tamponade
      effectiveness of intraocular silicone oil with that of an intraocular long-acting gas
      (initially sulfur hexafluoride [SF 6 ], later perfluoropropane [C 3 F 8 ]) for the management
      of retinal detachment complicated by proliferative vitreoretinopathy (PVR), using vitrectomy
      and associated techniques.

      To evaluate the ocular complications that result from the use of silicone oil and gas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The treatment of retinal detachment complicated by PVR remains controversial. Although some
      cases are managed successfully by pars plana vitrectomy and with temporary tamponade provided
      by intraocular gas, others eventually redetach with this technique. Preliminary reports
      indicate that prolonged tamponade with liquid silicone results in improved anatomical
      success, but the eventual visual outcome may be prejudiced by silicone-related complications,
      particularly glaucoma and keratopathy. The addition of hydraulic reattachment by simultaneous
      fluid/gas exchange to vitrectomy surgery has proved to be an important development. Although
      complications are few with these procedures, subsequent redetachment is frequent.

      The Silicone Study was a randomized trial to investigate the relative merits of silicone oil
      or gas as tamponade modalities. All study patients underwent vitrectomy and were randomized
      intraoperatively either to silicone oil or to gas. Two groups of eyes were entered into the
      study: eyes that had not had a prior vitrectomy (Group 1) and those that had undergone
      previous vitrectomy outside the study (Group 2).

      A critical element in the study was a standardized surgical procedure for PVR. This surgical
      procedure, intended to relieve retinal traction with vitrectomy techniques, was followed by
      assessment of the relief provided by an intraocular air tamponade. The eye was randomized to
      silicone oil or gas only after completion of the entire surgical procedure to eliminate
      investigator bias that might develop through knowledge of the treatment modality. Patients
      were examined 5 to 14 days following the randomization and again at 1, 3, 6, 12, 18, 24, and
      36 months after that date. Repeated surgery was permitted for either treatment modality. The
      Fundus Photograph Reading Center staff processed and analyzed photographs taken at all the
      clinics, graded the preoperative severity of PVR on the basis of baseline visit photographs,
      and confirmed the macular status at followup visits.

      End points of the study were visual acuity of 5/200 or greater and macular reattachment for 6
      months following the final surgical procedure. The successful outcomes and complication rates
      of the two modalities were compared.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1985</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Proliferative Vitreoretinopathy</condition>
  <condition>Retinal Detachment</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Perfluoropropane</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sulfur Hexafluoride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Silicone Oil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility criteria included but were not limited to PVR of Grade C-3 or greater according
        to the Retina Society Classification and visual acuity of light perception or better.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lean JS. Changing attitudes in United States to use of intravitreal silicone. Jpn J Ophthalmol. 1987;31(1):132-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3626172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glaser BM. Silicone oil for proliferative vitreoretinopathy. Does it help or hinder? Arch Ophthalmol. 1988 Mar;106(3):323-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3345147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azen SP, Irvine AR, Davis MD, Stern W, Lonn L, Hilton G, Schwartz A, Boone D, Quillen-Thomas B, Lyons M, et al. The validity and reliability of photographic documentation of proliferative vitreoretinopathy. Ophthalmology. 1989 Mar;96(3):352-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2652029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boone DC; Lai M; Azen S; Silicone Study Group; Clinical judgment and centralized data management., Controlled Clin Trials 1989;10:339</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irvine AR; Photographic documentation and grading of PVR, in Freeman HM, Tolentino FI (eds)., Proliferative Vitreoretinopathy, New York, Springer-Verlag 1989:105-109</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lean JS, Stern WH, Irvine AR, Azen SP. Classification of proliferative vitreoretinopathy used in the silicone study. The Silicone Study Group. Ophthalmology. 1989 Jun;96(6):765-71.</citation>
    <PMID>2662099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barlow W, Azen S. The effect of therapeutic treatment crossovers on the power of clinical trials. The Silicone Study Group. Control Clin Trials. 1990 Oct;11(5):314-26.</citation>
    <PMID>1963127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stern WH; Lean JS; Silicone Study Group; Intraocular silicone oil versus gas in the management of proliferative vitreoretinopathy (PVR): A multicenter clinical study, in Freeman HM, Tolentino FI (eds)., Proliferative Vitreoretinopathy, New York, Springer-Verlag 1989</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azen SP, Boone DC, Barlow W, McCuen BW, Walonker AF, Anderson MM, Lean JS, Mowery RL, Ryan SJ, Stern W. Methods, statistical features, and baseline results of a standardized, multicentered ophthalmologic surgical trial: the Silicone Study. Control Clin Trials. 1991 Jun;12(3):438-55.</citation>
    <PMID>1651213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Detachment</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitreoretinopathy, Proliferative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

