<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000148</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-49</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000148</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the long-range outcomes of sequences of interventions involving trabeculectomy and
      argon laser trabeculoplasty in eyes that have failed initial medical treatment for glaucoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In advanced glaucoma, medication alone no longer reduces intraocular pressure adequately, and
      the eye has field defects. Before 1980, some type of filtering surgery, such as
      trabeculectomy, was the usual method of intervention. Since then, laser trabeculoplasty has
      become a popular alternative. Sometimes the first intervention chosen succeeds in controlling
      pressure for many years; at other times, the success lasts only a few weeks or months.
      Because success is limited, some patients, over time, need to undergo a sequence of surgical
      interventions. Little is known about which sequence gives the best long-range outcome.

      The Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS) is designed to provide a comprehensive
      assessment of the long-range outcomes of medical and surgical management in advanced
      glaucoma. The study uses visual function status to compare two intervention sequences in
      managing the disease.

      Eligible eyes are randomly assigned to one of two intervention sequences: (1) trabeculectomy,
      followed by argon laser trabeculoplasty (ALT) should trabeculectomy fail, followed by a
      second trabeculectomy should ALT fail; or (2) ALT, followed by trabeculectomy should ALT
      fail, followed by another trabeculectomy should the first trabeculectomy fail. Antifibrotic
      agents may be used as an adjunct to trabeculectomy, but only in eyes with a previous history
      of invasive surgery. Eyes that fail the entire assigned sequence of interventions are managed
      at the discretion of the AGIS physician in collaboration with the patient.

      Interventions are supplemented with medical treatment as needed. A total of 789 eyes with
      advanced glaucoma have been enrolled. All patients are being followed under a standardized
      protocol for a minimum of 5 years to determine degree of visual function loss, failure rates
      of interventions, rates of complications, and need for supplemental therapy.

      After the initial intervention, followup examinations are scheduled at 1 week, 4 weeks, 3
      months, 6 months, and every 6 months thereafter. After second and third interventions,
      followup examinations are scheduled at 1 and 4 weeks. Additional visits are scheduled as
      necessary for the management of the disease.

      The primary outcome variable in AGIS is average percent of eyes with decrease of vision,
      where decrease of vision is a substantial decline of either visual field or visual acuity
      attributable to the effect of glaucoma. Secondary outcome variables include sustained
      decrease of vision, failure of interventions, number of prescribed glaucoma medications, and
      level of intraocular pressure. An ancillary study is assessing filtering bleb encapsulation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 1988</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Argon Laser Trabeculoplasty</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trabeculectomy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Men and women between the ages of 35 and 80 with open-angle glaucoma that was not
        successfully controlled by medication were eligible for enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University School of Medicine, Yale Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown University, University Ophthalmic Consultants of Washington, Eye Associates of Washington, D.C.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University, Emory Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Piedmont Hospital, Eye Consultants of Atlanta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Humana Health Plan Sykes Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois, Eye and Ear Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington Hospital Center, Washington Eye Physicians and Surgeons</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chevy Chase</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan, W.K. Kellogg Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sinai Hospital, Detroit, Franklin Eye Consultants</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southfield</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University, Department of Ophthalmology, Ophthalmic Surgeons and Consultants</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wills Eye Hospital, Glaucoma Service</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia Medical Center, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Virginia, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/pr798.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Blacks, Whites Benefit from Different Surgical Glaucoma Treatments</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS) Manual of Operations. Springfield, Virginia., National Technical Information Service, 1993;No. PB93-220192</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ederer F, Gaasterland DE, Sullivan EK; AGIS Investigators. The Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS): 1. Study design and methods and baseline characteristics of study patients. Control Clin Trials. 1994 Aug;15(4):299-325.</citation>
    <PMID>7956270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study. 2. Visual field test scoring and reliability. Ophthalmology. 1994 Aug;101(8):1445-55.</citation>
    <PMID>7741836</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS) Data Management Handbook. Springfield, Virginia., National Technical Information Service, Document, 1996;No. PB96-137120</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS): 3. Baseline characteristics of black and white patients. Ophthalmology. 1998 Jul;105(7):1137-45.</citation>
    <PMID>9663214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Advanced Glaucoma Intervention Study (AGIS): 4. Comparison of treatment outcomes within race. Seven-year results. Ophthalmology. 1998 Jul;105(7):1146-64.</citation>
    <PMID>9663215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 5, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

