<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-57</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Collaborative Longitudinal Evaluation of Keratoconus (CLEK) Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To describe the clinical course of keratoconus and to describe the relationships among its
      visual and physiological manifestations, including high- and low-contrast visual acuity,
      corneal curvature, slit lamp biomicroscopic findings, corneal scarring, and quality of life.

      To identify risk factors and protective factors that influence the severity and progression
      of keratoconus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Keratoconus is a bilateral, asymmetric, chronic, progressive ectasia of the cornea
      characterized by steepening and distortion of the cornea, thinning of the apical cornea,
      corneal scarring, and treatment-related sequelae, such as abrasions from contact lenses and
      surgical complications. Patients experience distorted vision that worsens with disease
      progression. Their vision is typically corrected with spectacles early in the disease and,
      later, with rigid contact lenses. Some patients eventually undergo corneal transplantation in
      one or both eyes. Keratoconus affects people in their prime earning years and profoundly
      affects their lives.

      Previous large-scale studies of keratoconus have focused on incidence and prevalence,
      etiologies, or the clinical management of keratoconus. Few have characterized the course of
      the disease and risk factors for its progression in large samples of keratoconus patients.
      The incidence of vision-threatening corneal scarring in keratoconus is unknown. Patient's
      most frequent questions--how rapidly their keratoconus will progress, how bad their vision
      will become, whether they will need corneal surgery, how successful their contact lenses will
      be--cannot be answered on the basis of the current body of knowledge.

      The need for a prospective, observational study of keratoconus patients is great. Results
      from this study will address keratoconus patient's unanswered questions and will enable eye
      care practitioners to manage this complex ocular disease better.

      The Collaborative Longitudinal Evaluation of Keratoconus (CLEK) Study is a multicenter,
      observational study of 1,209 keratoconus patients followed for 3 years.

      Patients are examined annually. Study measures include visual acuity, patient-reported
      quality of life, manifest refraction, keratometry, photodocumentation of the cornea to
      identify central corneal scarring, photodocumentation of the flattest contact lens that just
      clears the cornea, slit lamp biomicroscopy, and corneal topography. In rigid contact lens
      wearers, the fluorescein pattern of the patient's habitual contact lenses is photodocumented.

      Patients are examined at 15 clinical centers. The clinical centers enrolled 1,209 patients in
      12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 1995</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Keratoconus</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with keratoconus were eligible if they were at least 12 years old; had an
        irregular cornea as determined by keratometry, retinoscopy, or direct ophthalmoscopy in at
        least one eye; had Vogt's striae, Fleischer's ring, or corneal scarring characteristic of
        keratoconus in at least one eye; and planned to stay in the area for at least 3 years. They
        were ineligible if they had bilateral corneal transplants or bilateral nonkeratoconic eye
        disease (cataract, intraocular lenses, macular disease, or optic nerve disease other than
        glaucoma).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Berkeley, School of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berkeley</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94720-2020</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southern California College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fullerton</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92831</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jules Stein Eye Institute, University of California at Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095-7003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nova Southeastern University, Health Professions Division, College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33328</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois at Chicago, Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University, School of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bloomington</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>47405-3680</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri-St. Louis, School of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY State College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10036-8003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals of Cleveland, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University, College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210-1240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennsylvania College of Optometry, The Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northeastern Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scranton</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>18503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah, John Moran Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gundersen Lutheran</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Crosse</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>54601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barr JT, Gordon MO, Zadnik K, Pellican K, Edrington TB. Photodocumentation of corneal scarring. Collaborative Longitudinal Evaluation of Keratoconus Study Group. J Refract Surg. 1996 May-Jun;12(4):492-500.</citation>
    <PMID>8771545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edrington TB, Barr JT, Zadnik K, Davis LJ, Gundel RE, Libassi DP, McMahon TT, Gordon MO. Standardized rigid contact lens fitting protocol for keratoconus. Optom Vis Sci. 1996 Jun;73(6):369-75.</citation>
    <PMID>8807647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gundel RE, Libassi DP, Zadnik K, Barr JT, Davis L, McMahon TT, Edrington TB, Gordon MO. Feasibility of fitting contact lenses with apical clearance in keratoconus. Optom Vis Sci. 1996 Dec;73(12):729-32.</citation>
    <PMID>9002088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zadnik K, Barr JT, Gordon MO, Edrington TB. Biomicroscopic signs and disease severity in keratoconus. Collaborative Longitudinal Evaluation of Keratoconus (CLEK) Study Group. Cornea. 1996 Mar;15(2):139-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8925661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2001</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Keratoconus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

