<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000126</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-25</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000126</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ischemic Optic Neuropathy Decompression Trial Followup (IONDT Followup)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To follow all patients enrolled in the original Ischemic Optic Neuropathy Decompression Trial
      (IONDT) to determine (1) the incidence of non-arteritic ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION) in
      the second eye, (2) changes in visual acuity over time in both the study and second eye, and
      (3) other aspects of the natural history of NAION.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      NAION is the most common cause of acute optic nerve disease in the elderly, causing permanent
      and severe visual loss. No proven treatment currently exists to reverse or arrest this loss.
      There is no accepted method for the prevention or reduction of the likelihood of second eye
      involvement. NAION strikes both eyes in as many as 40 percent of affected patients (Beri et
      al. 1987), with a 2-year risk of about 25 percent (Steven Feldon, personal communication to
      SEK).

      IONDT compared optic nerve decompression surgery (ONDS), which was becoming a widely used
      treatment for NAION, with careful followup alone, in patients with newly diagnosed NAION. The
      rationale for the surgery was that NAION was caused by impaired blood flow to the optic nerve
      and that decompression surgery would restore vision by alleviating pressure surrounding the
      nerve. Because ONDS was fast becoming the standard of care, evaluation of the safety and
      efficacy of the procedure was tested in the context of a randomized clinical trial.

      Within 2 years of the start of the IONDT, the Data and Safety Monitoring Committee
      recommended cessation of the clinical trial recruitment. The National Institutes of Health
      issued a clinical alert to 25,000 ophthalmologists and neurologists describing the study
      findings that surgery was no better than careful followup and may be harmful (IONDT 1995). It
      was recommended that ONDS not be used in cases of NAION. Thus, the IONDT findings not only
      have led to a costly and ineffective surgery to be abandoned as a treatment for NAION, but
      also have left practitioners with a dearth of treatment choices.

      The IONDT is the first multicenter, prospective study of newly diagnosed patients with NAION.
      The baseline history and examination, which took place within 14 days of the onset of
      symptoms, used standardized methods and diagnostic criteria to collect data on all factors
      possibly relating to the etiology of NAION. In reports from previous studies that present
      data on both initial and final visual acuities, no data are available regarding change in
      visual acuity over time for individual patients. Where data are available on final visual
      acuity, reported rates of improvement are low, ranging from 0 percent to 33 percent for
      untreated eyes. The IONDT found, however, an improvement of three or more lines in 42.7
      percent of patients who received careful followup.

      NAION in both eyes has been reported in as few as 10.5 percent and as many as 73 percent of
      patients. In a study of bilateral NAION where all patients were prospectively logged, Beri et
      al. reported that 17.5 percent of patients developed bilateral disease at 1 year of followup
      and 34.5 percent developed it at 5 years. However, Beck et al., using a life table analysis
      on the same cohort reported by Beri et al., estimated the risk of bilateral NAION to be 12
      percent within 2 years and 19 percent within 5 years. The IONDT has so far similarly reported
      a 12 percent (25/216) incidence of bilateral NAION in its randomized patients. The incidence
      in the nonrandomized group, 91 percent of whom had visual acuity better than 20/64, is much
      lower at 4 percent (5/136).

      Thus, continued followup of the IONDT cohort is critically important to ascertain a clear
      picture of the natural history of NAION in terms of involvement of the second eye and
      long-term vision. Data obtained will be critical in understanding the etiology of the disease
      and in generating hypotheses for testing further treatments for the disease.

      The IONDT Followup Study will continue to monitor vision and other health outcomes in
      patients originally enrolled in the IONDT, whether randomized to one of the two treatment
      groups or whether followed as part of the natural history cohort. All IONDT patients were
      diagnosed with NAION within 14 days of onset of symptoms, have had a minimum of 2 years of
      continuous followup, and will be followed for an additional 4 years in the Followup Study.
      Patients will have annual visits at the original IONDT Clinical Center or, if necessary, with
      a surrogate provider. If NAION occurs in the second eye, the patient will be asked to visit
      the clinic for a special visit. The Coordinating Center will telephone the patients on a
      quarterly basis, between annual visits. Outcomes that will be examined include:

        -  incidence of NAION in the second eye,

        -  medical or ocular events surrounding the occurrence of NAION,

        -  visual acuity (measured using the New York Lighthouse charts).

      In the event of an NAION event in the second eye, the patient's visual field will be tested
      by using the Humphrey Perimeter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 1994</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Longitudinal</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Ischemic Optic Neuropathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgery</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        All living patients from the 420 patients originally enrolled in the IONDT have been asked
        to participate in the IONDT Followup Study. No new patients are being recruited.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Doheny Eye Institute, University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jules Stein Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory Eye Center, Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Illinois</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>W.K. Kellogg Eye Center, University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, Michigan State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William Beaumont Eye Institute, William Beaumont Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Royal Oak</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mason Institute of Ophthalmology, University of Missouri - Columbia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Louis University, Anheuser-Busch Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Health Science Center, Department of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carolinas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Cleveland Clinic Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allegheny General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Carolina, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Virginia, Department of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Virginia University, Department of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Non-arteritic Ischemic Optic Neuropathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Nerve Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuropathy, Ischemic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

