<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000160</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-62</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000160</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diabetic Retinopathy Study (DRS)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether photocoagulation helps prevent severe visual loss from proliferative
      diabetic retinopathy.

      To determine whether a difference exists in the efficacy and safety of argon versus xenon
      photocoagulation for proliferative diabetic retinopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      By the 1950s, diabetic retinopathy had become a leading cause of blindness and visual
      disability in the United States. The use of photocoagulation to treat proliferative
      retinopathy gained widespread use in ophthalmic practice following its introduction in 1959.
      However, only a few studies of photocoagulation incorporated any of the basic principles of
      controlled clinical trials, and these involved inadequate numbers of patients. Consequently,
      there has been inadequate evidence of the actual value of the procedure. Because of the
      clinical importance of diabetic retinopathy and the increasing use of photocoagulation in its
      management, the Diabetic Retinopathy Study (DRS) was begun in 1971. This randomized,
      controlled clinical trial involved more than 1,700 patients enrolled at 15 medical centers.

      One eye of each patient was randomly assigned to immediate photocoagulation and the other to
      followup without treatment, regardless of the course followed by either eye. The eye chosen
      for photocoagulation was randomly assigned to either of two treatment techniques, one using
      an argon laser and the other a xenon arc photocoagulator. Patients were followed at 4-month
      intervals according to a protocol that provided for measurement of best corrected visual
      acuity.

      Treatment was usually completed in one or two sittings and included scatter (panretinal)
      photocoagulation extending to or beyond the vortex vein ampulae. The argon treatment
      technique specified 800 to 1,600, 500-micron scatter burns of 0.1 second duration and direct
      treatment of new vessels whether on or within one disc diameter of the optic disc (NVD) or
      outside this area (NVE). Focal treatment was also applied to microaneurysms or other lesions
      thought to be causing macular edema. Followup treatment was applied as needed at 4-month
      intervals. The xenon technique was similar, but scatter burns were fewer in number, generally
      of longer duration, and stronger, and direct treatment was applied only to NVE on the surface
      of the retina.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1972</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <condition>Blindness</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Xenon Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Argon Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients were eligible if they had best corrected visual acuity of 20/100 or better in each
        eye and the presence of proliferative diabetic retinopathy in at least one eye or severe
        nonproliferative retinopathy in both eyes. They could not have had prior treatment with
        photocoagulation or pituitary ablation, and both eyes had to be suitable for
        photocoagulation. All eligible patients were younger than 70 years, and the examining
        physician assessed the outlook for survival and availability for 5 years of followup to be
        good.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/NEWS/clinicalalerts/alert-etdrs.asp</url>
    <description>Clinical Alert to Ophthalmologists—Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nei.nih.gov/news/pressreleases/drspressrelease.asp</url>
    <description>NEI Press Release-Laser Treatment Effective for Diabetic Retinopathy</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diabetic retinopathy study. Report Number 6. Design, methods, and baseline results. Report Number 7. A modification of the Airlie House classification of diabetic retinopathy. Prepared by the Diabetic Retinopathy. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1981 Jul;21(1 Pt 2):1-226.</citation>
    <PMID>7195893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Four risk factors for severe visual loss in diabetic retinopathy. The third report from the Diabetic Retinopathy Study. The Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1979 Apr;97(4):654-5.</citation>
    <PMID>426679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group; Photocoagulation treatment of proliferative diabetic retinopathy: A short report of long range results., Diabetic Retinopathy Study (DRS) Report Number 4. Proceedings of the 10th Congress of the International Diabetes Federation 1979</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Photocoagulation treatment of proliferative diabetic retinopathy: relationship of adverse treatment effects to retinopathy severity. Diabetic retinopathy study report no. 5. Dev Ophthalmol. 1981;2:248-61.</citation>
    <PMID>7262408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Photocoagulation treatment of proliferative diabetic retinopathy. Clinical application of Diabetic Retinopathy Study (DRS) findings, DRS Report Number 8. The Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group. Ophthalmology. 1981 Jul;88(7):583-600.</citation>
    <PMID>7196564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ederer F, Podgor MJ. Assessing possible late treatment effects in stopping a clinical trial early: a case study. Diabetic Retinopathy Study report No. 9. Control Clin Trials. 1984 Dec;5(4):373-81.</citation>
    <PMID>6394209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rand LI, Prud'homme GJ, Ederer F, Canner PL. Factors influencing the development of visual loss in advanced diabetic retinopathy. Diabetic Retinopathy Study (DRS) Report No. 10. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1985 Jul;26(7):983-91.</citation>
    <PMID>2409053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Preliminary report on effects of photocoagulation therapy. The Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group. Am J Ophthalmol. 1976 Apr;81(4):383-96.</citation>
    <PMID>944535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferris FL 3rd, Podgor MJ, Davis MD. Macular edema in Diabetic Retinopathy Study patients. Diabetic Retinopathy Study Report Number 12. Ophthalmology. 1987 Jul;94(7):754-60.</citation>
    <PMID>3658347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufman SC, Ferris FL 3rd, Swartz M. Intraocular pressure following panretinal photocoagulation for diabetic retinopathy. Diabetic Retinopathy Report No. 11. Arch Ophthalmol. 1987 Jun;105(6):807-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3555429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufman SC, Ferris FL 3rd, Seigel DG, Davis MD, DeMets DL. Factors associated with visual outcome after photocoagulation for diabetic retinopathy. Diabetic Retinopathy Study Report #13. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1989 Jan;30(1):23-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2912911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Indications for photocoagulation treatment of diabetic retinopathy: Diabetic Retinopathy Study Report no. 14. The Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group. Int Ophthalmol Clin. 1987 Winter;27(4):239-53.</citation>
    <PMID>2447027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group; Photocoagulation treatment of proliferative diabetic reinopathy: The second report from the Diabetic Retinopathy Study, Arch Ophthalmol 1978;85:81-106</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Vision Loss</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blindness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

