<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-64</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Branch Vein Occlusion Study</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether scatter argon laser photocoagulation can prevent the development of
      neovascularization.

      To determine whether peripheral scatter argon laser photocoagulation can prevent vitreous
      hemorrhage.

      To determine whether macular argon laser photocoagulation can improve visual acuity in eyes
      with macular edema reducing vision to 20/40 or worse.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Retinal branch vein occlusion (BVO) is the second most common retinal vascular disease after
      diabetic retinopathy. Many treatments for this disorder were attempted before 1977, but none
      were proven to be effective. The only treatment that seemed at all promising in preventing
      visual loss from BVO was laser photocoagulation.

      Approximately 500 patients were enrolled in the study. One-half were randomly assigned to
      treatment with argon laser photocoagulation; the other one-half remained untreated as
      controls. For BVO with or without neovascularization, scatter treatment of 100 to 400 laser
      burns was applied in the drainage area of the occluded vein site, avoiding the fovea and
      optic disc. Individual laser burns were 200 to 500 microns in diameter with an exposure time
      of 0.1 to 0.2 seconds. For macular edema, burns of 50 to 100 microns in diameter with
      exposure time of 0.05 to 0.1 seconds were used. A fluorescein angiogram less than 1 month old
      had to have been available for each patient. Treatment was performed under topical anesthesia
      using the argon laser to achieve a grid pattern over the area of capillary leakage identified
      by fluorescein in the macular region. Photocoagulation was extended no closer to the fovea
      than the edge of the foveal avascular zone and did not extend peripherally beyond the major
      vascular arcade. The efficacy of treatment was judged on the basis of visual acuity
      measurements as well as assessment of the subsequent development of neovascularization and/or
      vitreous hemorrhage. Patients were followed for at least 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1977</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Neovascularization, Pathologic</condition>
  <condition>Vitreous Hemorrhage</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Macular Argon Laser Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peripheral Scatter Argon Laser Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Scatter Argon Laser Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with three types of diagnoses were accepted:

          1. major BVO without neovascularization;

          2. major BVO with neovascularization;

          3. BVO with macular edema and reduced vision. All patients must have had onset of signs
             and/or symptoms of BVO less than 18 months before the initial visit, vision of 5/200
             or better, and sufficient clarity of the ocular media to permit confirmation of the
             condition with fundus photography. Other eligibility criteria apply to each of the
             three major groups as well as special cases such as the occurrence of bilateral
             disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Argon laser photocoagulation for macular edema in branch vein occlusion. The Branch Vein Occlusion Study Group. Am J Ophthalmol. 1984 Sep 15;98(3):271-82.</citation>
    <PMID>6383055</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Argon laser scatter photocoagulation for prevention of neovascularization and vitreous hemorrhage in branch vein occlusion. A randomized clinical trial. Branch Vein Occlusion Study Group. Arch Ophthalmol. 1986 Jan;104(1):34-41.</citation>
    <PMID>2417579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neovascularization, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitreous Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

