<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on February 12, 2019</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000161</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEI-63</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000161</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Trials of Vitamin Supplements and Eye Disease</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Eye Institute (NEI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether vitamin E supplementation reduces the risk of cataract and age-related
      macular degeneration (AMD) in women.

      To determine whether vitamin C supplementation reduces the risk of cataract and AMD in women.

      To determine whether beta-carotene supplementation reduces the risk of cataract and AMD in
      women.

      To determine whether alternate day, low-dose aspirin reduces the risk of cataract and AMD in
      women.

      To identify potential risk factors for cataract and AMD including cigarette smoking, alcohol
      intake, blood pressure, blood cholesterol, cardiovascular disease, height, body mass index,
      and diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cataract and AMD are two of the most important causes of visual impairment in older
      Americans. Approximately 3.3 million people have visual impairment due to cataract. Cataract
      extraction, although one of the safest and most successful of all operations, is now the most
      frequently performed operation in the United States among persons older than 60, costing an
      estimated $1.5 billion annually. AMD is the leading cause of new cases of blindness in
      persons aged 65 and older. Approximately 25 percent of persons aged 65 years and older have
      signs of AMD. The pathogenesis of AMD, however, is only partly understood, and its etiology
      remains obscure. For most patients, there is no available treatment. The public health burden
      imposed by cataract and AMD will only increase in the coming decades as the U.S. population
      ages.

      These randomized, double-masked, placebo-controlled trials will test the hypotheses that
      supplementation with antioxidant vitamins and with low-dose aspirin reduces the risk of
      age-related cataract and AMD. The study populations are the Women's Health Study (WHS) and
      the Women's Antioxidant Cardiovascular Study (WACS). The WHS is a randomized, double-masked,
      placebo-controlled trial using a 2x2 factorial design to test low-dose aspirin (100 mg on
      alternate days) and vitamin E (600 IU on alternate days) in the primary prevention of
      cardiovascular disease (CVD) and cancer. It is being conducted among 39,876 apparently
      healthy female health professionals age 45 years and older. The WACS is a randomized,
      double-masked, placebo-controlled secondary prevention trial using a 2x2x2x2 factorial design
      to test antioxidant vitamins (vitamins E [600 IU on alternate days] and C [500 mg daily],
      beta carotene [50 mg on alternate days]), and a combination of folate (800 mg daily), vitamin
      B6 (25 mg daily), and vitamin B12 (1 mg daily) among women who are at high risk for CVD
      morbidity and mortality. It is being conducted among 8,171 female health professionals, ages
      40 years or older, who either have preexisting CVD or have at least three coronary risk
      factors and therefore are at high risk for the development of CVD.

      In addition to the randomized comparisons, the investigators will also examine risk factors
      for age-related cataract and AMD in these two populations. Factors to be examined include
      cigarette smoking, alcohol intake, blood pressure, blood cholesterol, cardiovascular disease,
      height, body mass index, diabetes, and dietary factors.

      In each study population, followup questionnaires were sent at 6 and 12 months after
      randomization and every 12 months thereafter requesting information about development of
      relevant study end points including cataract and AMD and participant compliance with study
      medications. Reported diagnoses of cataract and AMD are confirmed by medical record review.
      The primary analysis for the randomized studies will be incidence of AMD or cataract in the
      treatment and placebo groups. Survival analysis will be used to determine whether there is a
      difference in time to AMD or cataract diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 1993</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aspirin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Beta-Carotene</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin C</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin E</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Women's Health Study:

        A participant must have met all of the following criteria:

        (a) female; (b) aged 45 years or older; (c) postmenopausal or with no intention of becoming
        pregnant; (d) no reported personal history of cardiovascular disease, cancer (other than
        non-melanoma skin cancer), gout, peptic ulcer, chronic renal or liver disease, or other
        serious illness precluding participation; (e) no reported history of serious side effects
        to the study treatments; (f) not currently taking aspirin, aspirin containing medication,
        or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) more than 1 day per week or, if so doing,
        willing to forego use of these medications; (g) not currently taking individual supplements
        of vitamin E or beta carotene more than 1 day per week; (h) not currently taking
        anticoagulants or corticosteroids.

        Women's Antioxidant Cardiovascular Study:

        Potentially eligible female health professionals for WACS were identified from the pool of
        respondents to the Women's Health Study initial mailing and must have met the following
        criteria:

        (a) female; (b) date of birth before January 1, 1955; (c) a reported history of myocardial
        infarction (MI), stroke (CVA), angina pectoris (AP), coronary artery bypass grafting
        (CABG), percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PCTA), transient ischemic attack (TIA),
        carotid endarterectomy (CEA), or peripheral artery surgery (PAS); (d) no history of cancer
        (except non-melanoma skin cancer) within the past 10 years and no active liver disease or
        cirrhosis; (e) pregnancy physiologically impossible due to menopause (natural or surgical)
        or tubal ligation, or the participant does not intend to become pregnant in the future as
        indicated on the initial WHS questionnaire; (f) no current use of a vitamin K-depleting
        anticoagulant agent (e.g., Coumadin). Individuals taking aspirin or other NSAIDs were not
        excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>September 2001</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Age-Related Macular Degeneration</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Beta Carotene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carotenoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

